yes the title is correct and no it is
not clickbait in fact there are many
incredible things that your body does to
protect you from disease and there's
even something that you can do that has
an astonishing heart attack protecting
effect it's truly incredible it's called
cardiac preconditioning so what is it
how does it happen how can you give
yourself more heart attacks to prevent
heart attacks did you ever expect to
hear those words strung together we need
to start at the heart attack there are
different forms of heart attack but the
most common is es schic meaning your
coronary arteries of the heart are
somehow blocked and there's no blood
flow reaching the downstream sections of
the heart this lack of nutrients and
oxygen ultimately leads your heart cells
to die and if that happens on a mass
scale you ain't going to be up right for
much longer now the reason I call
cardiac preconditioning incredible is
because it's a technique by which you
can reduce the future heart attack size
by 40% or more that's the difference
between death and life the difference
between being hobbled for life and a
normal life the first ever study on this
phenomenon dating back to the 1980s the
researchers showed as we can see here
that A Heart That was preconditioned had
a four times smaller heart attack than
the hearts that were not preconditioned
there are some added uh nuances that
we'll get into in this particular data
later but for now just know that
preconditioning the heart protects
massively when an actual heart attack
occurs okay so what is preconditioning
preconditioning is putting the heart in
a situation that is very similar to a
heart attack essentially it's a short
period of esema as defined earlier in
the heart attack that creates lasting
protection if a person experiences a
true heart attack fascinatingly this
effect has been demonstrated in
according to these researchers in mouse
rat guinea pig rabbit dog Pig and
indirectly in humans as well there's a
strong consistency across species okay
so what exactly happens to your heart
then what can you do to cause cardiac
preconditioning in your own heart first
some of the mechanisms and then we'll
rely on this scientific review for
clarity for one there are many
extracellular that means outside the
cell signals that affect your heart
cells from adenosine molecules to
catacol amines like epinephrine and
several other molecules they bind to
their individual receptors which
activates a grouping of key proteins
called
phospholipases these phospholipases they
enzymes convert molecules of pip 2 to
ip3 and dag molecules now you don't need
to remember all the names just that
there's a Cascade of events that happens
inside the cell from there dags activate
a Master protein called pkc this pkc
protein activates further Downstream
proteins called transcription factors
which translocate or move to the nucleus
of your cells and bind specific genes
that contain the genetic information for
proteins that will protect your heart
cells if serious esea occurs for example
one such protein is bcl2 if your cells
incur too much cellular stress they can
undergo cell death called apoptosis this
is partly mediated by a family of
proteins called the BCL family proteins
some encourage apoptosis and some block
it bcl2 blocks it so preconditioning
increases the concentration of bcl2 in
the heart muscle cells protecting them
from a cell death fate or another
protein that is produced is called inos
which is an enzyme responsible for the
generation of nitric oxide this nitric
oxide opens blood vessels and allows
more blood flow through a critical
Factor when there's a blockage stopping
blood flow so if you're interested I'll
be covering more on the mechanisms
including mitochondrial ones in the
extended version of this video included
for the physionic Insiders it's linked
in the description now while this has
been shown experimentally by literally
clamping blood vessels and starving the
heart in different animal models we are
about to reach into our chest and clamp
Our arteries so what else can be done to
increase cardiac
preconditioning and there's an important
caveat that we have to keep in mind that
I'll get into in a minute too if we pop
up in this review the researchers
indicate that while the mechanisms are
slightly different cardiac
preconditioning can occur through
exercise unfortunately there hasn't been
enough research on the types of exercise
to get into much of the details however
it seems clear that aerobic endurance
exercise is likely the primary way of
inducing this cardio protection in fact
there have been some preclinical data
that also indicate high-intensity
interval training could offer this
cardiac preconditioning benefit these
researchers even point out that there's
strong evidence pointing to people who
exercise regularly are more likely to
survive heart attacks this might be one
of the major mechanisms for that
although it doesn't exclude other
factors as for the caveat it's in
relation to this data that we went over
this was measured 40 minutes after the
heart attack happened meaning if the
heart attack can can be resolved in 40
minutes there's a significant reduction
in the overall damage due to
preconditioning however when researchers
do the same experiment and wait longer
to resolve as seen here there's no
protective effect the time frame for
that experiment was 3 hours this was an
animal model so we don't know if this
carries over to humans in those exact
numbers but it offers a glimpse that
cardiac preconditioning isn't a forever
protection still even a 40-minute window
could be a massive one when discussing
potentially fatal heart attacks oh also
one more fascinating piece uh it's
believed that the heart conditioning
effects could extend up to 72 hours so
for example exercising and then having
this cardiac preconditioning effect
lasts for days after exercise so imagine
if you exercise every day or every other
day that means constant protection
powerful stuff that all is due to
changes called late cardiac
preconditioning again mechanisms that
I'll be discussing in the extended
version of this video for the physionic
Insiders at any rate heart health is
critical and I cover so much more in
this video right here I'll speak with
you over there thanks for tuning in